A Guide to the Governor John Stewart Battle Executive records, 1950-1954
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor John Stewart Battle Executive records, 1950-1954
The Library of Virginia
24504
80 cu. ft. (172 boxes)
Virginia. Governor (1950-1954: Battle)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the Governor, June and July 1956.
Biographical Information
John Stewart Battle was born in New Bern, North Carolina on 11 July 1890. He served in the Virginia House of Delegates from 1930-1933, in the Virginia Senate from 1934-1949, and as Governor from 1950-1954. He died in Charlottesville, Va., 9 April 1972.
Scope and Content
The Executive Papers of Governor John S. Battle are housed in 172 boxes. The collection is arranged into eight (8) series. Series have been designated for: I. Reports on Audits. II. State Government. III. Extraditions. IV. Federal Government. V. General Assembly. VI. General Correspondence. VII. Invitations. VIII. Judicial. These records include applications, appointments, audits, correspondence, executive orders, extraditions, invitations, invoices, minutes, proclamations, recommendations, reports, and speeches. These records document the gubernatorial administration of John S. Battle from 18 January 1950 to 19 January 1954.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Reports on Audits
Series II. State Government
Series III. Extraditions
Series IV. Federal Government
Series V. General Assembly
Series VI. General Correspondence
Series VII. Invitations
Series VIII. Judicial
Contents List
- Series I: Reports on Audit, 1950-1954., Extent: 20 cu. ft. [45 boxes]. (Box 1-45)
  The Reports on Audits are housed in 45 boxes and are arranged by year and subdivided by locality and state agency.
  - Agencies, Alcoholic Beverage Control Board-Lynchburg State College, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Agencies, Manassas High School-Virginia Truck Experiment Station, 1950-1951 (Box 2)
  - Counties and Cities, Accomack-Bath, 1950-1951 (Box 3)
  - Counties and Cities, Bedford-Caroline, 1949-1951 (Box 4)
  - Counties and Cities, Carroll-Danville, 1950-1951 (Box 5)
  - Counties and Cities, Dickenson-Fredericksburg, 1950-1951 (Box 6)
  - Counties and Cities, Giles-Henry, 1950-1951 (Box 7)
  - Counties and Cities, Herndon-Lynchburg, 1950-1951 (Box 8)
  - Counties and Cities, Madison-Newport News, 1950-1951 (Box 9)
  - Counties and Cities, Norfolk-Petersburg, 1949-1951 (Box 10)
  - Counties and Cities, Pittsylvania-Radford, 1950-1951 (Box 11)
  - Counties and Cities, Rappahannock-Russell, 1950-1951 (Box 12)
  - Counties and Cities, Scott-Tazewell, 1950-1951 (Box 13)
  - Counties and Cities, Warren-York, 1950-1951 (Box 14)
  - Audits by Code Number, 111-212 (Box 15)
  - Audits by Code Number, 215-604, 1950-1951 (Box 16)
  - Audits by Code Number, 605-1001, 1950-1951 (Box 17)
  - Agencies, ABC-Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries, 1952 (Box 17)
  - Agencies, DeJarnette State Sanatorium-Medical College of Virginia, 1952 (Box 18)
  - Agencies, New London Academy-Textbook Fund, 1952 (Box 19)
  - Agencies, Textbook Fund-Virginia State Library, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Counties and Cities, Accomack-Augusta, 1952 (Box 20)
  - Counties and Cities, Bath-Cumberland, 1952 (Box 21)
  - Counties and Cities, Damascus-Gretna, 1952 (Box 22)
  - Counties and Cities, Halifax-Montgomery, 1952 (Box 23)
  - Counties and Cities, Nansemond-Pulaski, 1952 (Box 24)
  - Counties and Cities, Radford-Tazewell, 1952 (Box 25)
  - Counties and Cities, Warren-York, 1952 (Box 26)
  - Agencies, ABC-Juvenile and Domestic Relations, 1953 (Box 26)
  - Agencies, Madison College-Trial Justice Court, 1953 (Box 27)
  - Agencies, Unemployment Compensation Commission-Virginia State Library, 1953 (Box 28)
  - Counties and Cities, Accomack-Dinwiddie, 1953 (Box 28)
  - Counties and Cities, Essex-Lynchburg, 1953 (Box 29)
  - Counties and Cities, Madison-Richmond, 1953 (Box 30)
  - Counties and Cities, Roanoke-York, 1953 (Box 31)
  - Agencies, ABC-Dept. of Welfare and Institutions, 1954 (Box 32)
  - Agencies, District Home-Piedmont Sanatorium, 1954 (Box 33)
  - Agencies, Police Court-Supreme Court of Appeals, 1954 (Box 34)
  - Agencies, Textbook Fund-University of Virginia, 1954 (Box 35)
  - Agencies, Violations Bureau-Woodrow Wilson Rehabilitation Center, 1954 (Box 36)
  - Counties and Cities, Accomack-Amelia 1954 (Box 36)
  - Counties and Cities, Amherst-Buena Vista, 1954 (Box 37)
  - Counties and Cities, Campbell-Cumberland, 1954 (Box 38)
  - Counties and Cities, Damascus-Gloucester, 1954 (Box 39)
  - Counties and Cities, Goochland-King William, 1954 (Box 40)
  - Counties and Cities, Lancaster-New Kent, 1954 (Box 41)
  - Counties and Cities, Newport News-Portsmouth, 1954 (Box 42)
  - Counties and Cities, Powhatan-Rockingham, 1954 (Box 43)
  - Counties and Cities, Russell-Warwick, 1954 (Box 44)
  - Counties and Cities, Washington-York, 1954 (Box 45)
  - Counties and Cities, A-Y, 1955 (Box 45)
- Series II: State government, 1950-1954., Extent: 20 cu. ft. [44 boxes]. (Box 46-89)
  The State Government records are housed in 44 boxes and are arranged alphabetically by agency or subject. Subjects include: Alcoholic Beverage Control Board, Boards, Commissions (including Art Commission and Hampton Roads Sanitation Commission), Virginia Conservation Commission, Virginia Corporation Commission, Education (Advisory Research Committee on School Construction, Superintendent of Public Instruction, and colleges and universities), Governor's Mansion, Grounds and Buildings, Department of Health, Highways, Department of Mental Hygiene and Hospitals (includes mental hospitals), Military Affairs (Adjutant General), Retirement (Virginia Retirement System and Virginia Supplemental Retirement System), State Police, Taxation, Unemployment Compensation Commission, Virginia Ports Authority, Welfare and Institutions (Corrections, Penitentiary, and Parole Board), and Public Welfare.
  - Accounts and Purchases, Dept. of (Box 46-47)
  - Agriculture (Box 48)
  - Agriculture and Immigration (Box 48-49)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control (Box 50)
  - Auditor of Public Accounts (Box 50)
  - Barter Theatre (Box 50)
  - Boards (Box 50-52)
  - Budget, Division of (Box 52-53)
  - Commissions, Advisory Council on the Virginia Economy, 1950 (Box 54)
  - Commissions, Advisory Council on the Virginia Economy, 1951 (Box 55)
  - Commissions, Advisory Council on the Virginia Economy, 1952-1953 (Box 56)
  - Commissions, Advisory Legislative Council (Box 56)
  - Commissions, Art-Code Recodification (Box 57)
  - Commissions, Elizabeth River Tunnel-Game and Inland Fisheries (Box 58)
  - Commissions, Hampton Roads-Wrestling and Boxing (Box 59)
  - Conservation and Development-Conservation Commission, Virginia (Box 60)
  - Conservation Commission, Virginia (Box 61)
  - Corporation Commission (Box 62-64)
  - Common Glory (Box 65)
  - Education, Advisory Research Committee on School Construction-Public Schools (Box 65)
  - Education, Program (Box 66)
  - Education, Rehabilitation and Adult Education-Woodrow Wilson Rehabilitation Center (Box 67)
  - Education, Schools, College of William and Mary-Medical College of Virginia (Box 68)
  - Education, University of Virginia-Mary Washington College (Box 69)
  - Education, Virginia Military Institute-Virginia Polytechnic Institute (Box 70)
  - Education, Virginia Polytechnic Institute-Virginia Truck Experiment Station (Box 71)
  - Governor's Mansion-Governor's Office (Box 71)
  - Governor's Office-Grounds and Buildings (Box 72)
  - Grounds and Buildings (Box 73)
  - Gunston Hall (Box 73)
  - Health, Dept. of (Box 73)
  - Health, Dept. of (Box 74)
  - Highways, Commissioner-Appointment (Box 74)
  - Highways, Commissioner-Recommendations (Box 75)
  - Highways, Ferry Control-York Bridge (Box 76)
  - Highways, Governor's Highway Safety Committee (Box 77)
  - Industrial Commission of Virginia (Box 78)
  - Labor and Industry (Box 78)
  - Mental Hygiene and Hospitals, Dept. of (Box 79)
  - Mental Hygiene and Hospitals, Hospitals, Central State-Western State (Box 80)
  - Merit System Council (Box 80)
  - Military Affairs (Box 80)
  - Motor Vehicles (Box 81)
  - Personnel, Director of (Box 82)
  - Retirement (Box 82)
  - Secretary of the Commonwealth (Box 83)
  - State Police (Box 83)
  - Statutory Research and Drafting (Box 84)
  - Taxation (Box 84)
  - Treasury (Box 84)
  - Unemployment Compensation Commission (Box 84)
  - Virginia Museum of Fine Arts (Box 85)
  - Virginia State Bar (Box 86)
  - Virginia Ports Authority (Box 86)
  - Virginia State Library (Box 86)
  - Welfare and Institutions, Board of-Dept. of Welfare and Institutions (Box 87)
  - Welfare and Institutions, Parole Board (Box 88-89)
  - Welfare, Public (Box 89)
- Series III: Extraditions, 1950-1954., Extent: 10 cu. ft. [27 boxes]. (Box 90-116)
  The Extradition records are housed in 27 boxes and are arranged alphabetically. Following the extradition records is a petition for the Martinsville Seven and records for the removal of political disabilities.
  - A (Box 90)
  - B-Bee (Box 91)
  - Bel-Bri (Box 92)
  - Bro-Chat (Box 93)
  - Chav-Cra (Box 94)
  - Cre-Dil (Box 95)
  - Dim-E (Box 96)
  - F-Ga (Box 97)
  - Ge-Gra (Box 98)
  - Gre-Harr (Box 99)
  - Harv-Hoy (Box 100)
  - Hub-Kel (Box 101)
  - Ken-Leo (Box 102)
  - Lew-Lu (Box 103)
  - Mc-Mar (Box 104)
  - Mas-Mi (Box 105)
  - Mo-No (Box 106)
  - Nu-Pel (Box 107)
  - Pen-Ra (Box 108)
  - Re-Ry (Box 109)
  - S-Sm (Box 110)
  - Sn-Taw (Box 111)
  - Tay-V (Box 112)
  - W-Wilc (Box 113)
  - Wilk-Z (Box 114)
  - Petition, Martinsville Seven (Box 115)
  - Removal of Political Disabilities, A-L (Box 115)
  - Removal of Political Disabilities, M-Z (Box 116)
- Series IV: Federal Government, 1950-1954., Extent: 3 cu. ft. [7 boxes]. (Box 116-122)
  The Federal Government records are housed in 7 boxes and are arranged alphabetically by agency or subject. Subjects include: Army, Civilian Defense, Executive Departments, and Rent.
  - Aid -Army (Box 116)
  - Atlantic Command (Box 116)
  - Coast Guard (Box 116)
  - Commissions (Box 116)
  - Congress and Senate (Box 117)
  - Civilian Defense (Box 117-118)
  - Executive Departments, Agriculture-Defense (Box 119)
  - Executive Departments, Health-U.S. Government, Deeds (Box 120)
  - Legislation (Box 121)
  - Power Commission (Box 121)
  - Rent (Box 121-122)
  - United States President (Box 122)
  - Presidential Inauguration, 1953 (Box 122)
- Series V: General Assembly, 1950-1954., Extent: 4 cu. ft. [8 boxes]. (Box 122-130)
  The General Assembly records are housed in 8 boxes and are arranged by General Assembly session followed by subjects. Records include: notes on bills, Commissions, Virginia Advisory Legislative Council, Redistricting, Reports, and Resignations.
  - 1950 (Box 122-123)
  - 1950, House, Legislature, Senate (Box 124)
  - 1951 (Box 125)
  - 1952 (Box 125)
  - 1952, House, Legislature (Box 126)
  - 1952, Senate, Extra Session, Special Session (Box 127)
  - Commissions (Box 128-129)
  - Virginia Advisory Legislative Council, 1948-1950 (Box 129)
  - Governor's Information (Box 129)
  - Juvenile and Domestic Relations (Box 129)
  - Hospital and Medical Service Assistant (Box 129)
  - House of Delegates (Box 129)
  - Matters relating to Higher Education (Box 129)
  - Medical Education in Virginia (Box 129)
  - Model YMCA (Box 129)
  - New State Office building (Box 129)
  - Redistricting (Box 129)
  - Reports (Box 129-130)
  - Request (Box 130)
  - Research Committee on School Buildings (Box 130)
  - Resignations (Box 130)
  - House Joint Resolution, Oysters (Box 130)
  - Senate, Clerk (Box 130)
  - Study of Organization (Box 130)
  - Teachers Salaries (Box 130)
  - Transcribing of evidence in criminal cases (Box 130)
  - Williamsburg, Convening of Joint Session (Box 130)
  - War memorial letters (Box 130)
  - World War II Memorial (Box 130)
- Series VI: General Correspondence, 1950-1954., Extent: 15 cu. ft. [29 boxes]. (Box 130-158)
  The General Correspondence are housed in 29 boxes and are arranged alphabetically by subject. Notable subjects include: Civil Rights, Executive Orders, Proclamations, Requests, Southern Governors, Statements, and Taxes.
  - Advertising (Box 130)
  - Airport (Box 130)
  - American Heritage Foundation (Box 130)
  - American Korean Foundation (Box 130)
  - American Legion (Box 130)
  - American Red Cross (Box 131)
  - Appointments with Governor (Box 131)
  - Audit (Box 131)
  - Bazile (Box 131)
  - Bill of Rights (Box 131)
  - Bonds (Box 131)
  - Booker T. Washington Birthplace Memorial (Box 131)
  - Boy Scouts of America (Box 131)
  - Cape Henry Celebration (Box 131)
  - Care (Box 131)
  - Carwile, Howard H. (Box 131)
  - Chamber of Commerce (Box 131)
  - Chamber of Commerce (Box 132)
  - Christian Rural Overseas Program (CROP) (Box 132)
  - Civil Rights (Box 132)
  - Colonial Williamsburg (Box 132)
  - Commissioner of Deeds (Box 132)
  - Commissions Issued (Box 132)
  - Communism-Propaganda (Box 132)
  - Community fund (Box 132)
  - Confederate Museum (Box 132)
  - Council of State Governments (Box 133)
  - Crime (Box 133)
  - Crusade for Freedom (Box 133)
  - Daylight Savings Time (Box 133)
  - Delegates designated by Governor (Box 133)
  - Democratic State Central Committee (Box 134)
  - Democratic National Committee (Box 134)
  - Doctors (Box 134)
  - Economic Stabilization Agency (Box 134)
  - Election (Box 134)
  - Employment Service (Box 134)
  - Executive Orders, 1946-1948 (Box 134)
  - Executive Orders, 1950-1952 (Box 134)
  - Federation of Women's Clubs (Box 134)
  - Foreign Correspondence (Box 134)
  - Gambling (Box 134)
  - Girl Scouts of America (Box 135)
  - Government of the District of Columbia (Box 135)
  - Governor's Conferences, 1950-1953 (Box 135)
  - Governors of other states (Box 136)
  - Griffenhagen, Surveys (Box 136)
  - Gunston Hall (Box 136)
  - Hampton Roads (Box 136)
  - Holiday Information (Box 136)
  - Home for Needy Confederate Women (Box 136)
  - Inaugural, 1950 (Box 136)
  - Indian Problems (Box 136)
  - Interagency Committee on Recreation (Box 136)
  - Interstate Oil Compact Commission (Box 137)
  - Invitations, Honorary positions (Box 137)
  - Izaak Walton League (Box 137)
  - Jamestown Society (Box 137)
  - Korean Foundation (Box 137)
  - Labor (Box 137)
  - Law enforcement (Box 137)
  - League of Virginia Counties (Box 137)
  - League of Virginia Municipalities (Box 137)
  - League of Women Voters (Box 137)
  - Legal matters (Box 138)
  - Legislative Action, Requests for (Box 138)
  - Letters of Congratulations (Box 138)
  - Letters of Endorsement (Box 138)
  - Letters of Greeting (Box 138)
  - Letters of Introduction (Box 138)
  - Letters of Recommendations (Box 138)
  - Letters sent to Heads of Departments, Mimeograph copies (Box 138)
  - Liberty Bell (Box 139)
  - Lists (Box 139)
  - Local affairs (Box 139)
  - March of Dimes (Box 139)
  - Maritime Exchange, Hampton Roads (Box 139)
  - Mid-Century Conference on Resources (Box 139)
  - Mother's Day (Box 139)
  - Mount Vernon (Box 139)
  - National Cancer Foundation (Box 140)
  - National Capitol Park and Planning Commission (Box 140)
  - National Democratic Committee (Box 140)
  - National Democratic Convention, 1952 (Box 140)
  - National Employ the Physically Handicapped Week (Box 140)
  - National Freedom Day (Box 140)
  - National Rivers and Harbors Congress (Box 140)
  - National Safety Council (Box 140)
  - National Society, Daughters of American Revolution (Box 140)
  - Northern Virginia Regional Planning and Economic Development Commission (Box 140)
  - Notaries (Box 140)
  - Old Appointment sheets (Box 140)
  - Patrick Henry Memorial Foundation (Box 141)
  - Pocahontas (Box 141)
  - Political matters (Box 141)
  - President's Highway Safety Conference (Box 141)
  - President's Water Resources Policy (Box 141)
  - Press (Box 141)
  - Price control (Box 141)
  - Proclamation data (Box 142)
  - Proclamations (Box 142)
  - Racial (Box 142)
  - Richmond, Fredericksburg, and Potomac Investments (Box 143)
  - Radio Broadcasts (Box 143)
  - Radio, W.M.B.G. (Box 143)
  - Radio, W.R.N.L. (Box 143)
  - Radio, W.R.V.A. (Box 143)
  - Reciprocal agreements (Box 143)
  - Reciprocity Board (Box 143)
  - Religious Worship (Box 143)
  - Rent problems (Box 143)
  - Requests, 1950 (Box 143)
  - Requests, 1950 (Box 144)
  - Requests, 1951 (Box 145-146)
  - Requests, 1952 (Box 147)
  - Requests, Miscellaneous (Box 148-149)
  - Requests, Constitutions (Box 149)
  - Requests, Flags (Box 149)
  - Requests, Copies of Governor's messages (Box 149)
  - Requests, Publications (Box 149)
  - Resources for the Future, Incorporated (Box 149)
  - Retirements (Box 149)
  - Richmond (Box 149)
  - Safety (Box 150)
  - Small business (Box 150)
  - Social events (Box 150)
  - Social Security Board (Box 150)
  - Sons of the American Revolution (Box 150)
  - Southern Governors (Box 150)
  - Southern Governor's Conference (Box 150)
  - Southern Regional Education Board (Box 151-152)
  - Speeches made by the Governor (Box 153)
  - Statements (Box 153-154)
  - Stratford Journal (Box 154)
  - Strikes (Box 154)
  - Taxes (Box 154)
  - Thanksgiving Celebration (Box 155)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation (Box 155)
  - Tickets (Box 155)
  - Tidelands (Box 155)
  - Tidewater Automobile Association (Box 155)
  - Tobacco Bowl Festival (Box 155)
  - Traffic, Highways (Box 155)
  - Traffic, Violations (Box 156)
  - Treaty (Box 156)
  - Tuberculosis (Box 156)
  - United China Relief (Box 157)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy (Box 157)
  - United Nations Organization (Box 157)
  - Veterans Administration Facility (Box 157)
  - Veterans Advisory Committee (Box 157)
  - Veterans Affairs (Box 157)
  - Veterans Bonus (Box 157)
  - Veterans Confederate (Box 157)
  - Veterans Disabled American (Box 157)
  - Veterans Educational and Vocational (GI Bill) (Box 157)
  - Veterans of Foreign Wars (Box 157)
  - Veterans Spanish American (Box 157)
  - Virginia Beach (Box 157)
  - Virginia Conference of Social Work (Box 157)
  - Virginia Council on Health and Medical Care (Box 157)
  - Virginia District Y.M.C.A. (Box 157)
  - Virginia Education Association (Box 157)
  - Virginia Federation of Garden Clubs (Box 157)
  - Virginia Highway Users Association (Box 157)
  - Virginia Historical Society (Box 157)
  - Virginia Manufacturer's Association (Box 158)
  - Virginia Military District (Box 158)
  - Virginia Mothers Committee, 1950 (Box 158)
  - Virginia State Teachers Association (Box 158)
  - Virginia Travel Council (Box 158)
  - Virginia Travel Magazine (Box 158)
  - Virginia Tuberculosis Association (Box 158)
  - Virginia Women's Club (Box 158)
  - Voting (Box 158)
  - J.H. Wyse, Disaster Compact (Box 158)
  - White House Conference, 1950 (Box 158)
  - White House Conference, Child welfare (Box 158)
  - World Federation (Box 158)
  - World Medical Association (Box 158)
  - Young Democrats of Virginia (Box 158)
  - Youth and Government Program (Box 158)
- Series VII: Invitations, 1950-1954., Extent: 4 cu. ft. [8 boxes]. (Box 158-165)
  The Invitations are housed in 8 boxes and are arranged chronologically.
  - 1950 January-February (Box 158)
  - 1950 March-July (Box 159)
  - 1950 August-December (Box 160)
  - 1951 January-July (Box 161)
  - 1951 August-1952 April (Box 162)
  - 1952 May-1953 January (Box 163)
  - 1953 February-September (Box 164)
  - 1953 October-December (Box 165)
- Series VIII: Judicial, 1950-1954., Extent: 4 cu. ft. [8 boxes]. (Box 165-172)
  The Judicial records are housed in 8 boxes and are arranged by Court.
  - Attorney General (Box 165)
  - Circuit Courts (Box 166)
  - Corporation Court (Box 167)
  - Estate of Granville P. Meade (Box 167)
  - Judges (Box 167)
  - Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia (Box 168)
  - Voucher Accounts (Box 169-170)
  - Invoices (Box 171)
  - Invoices-Requisitions (Box 172)